<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Time complaining, giueth a most godly admonition, and very profitable instruction to England in this our dangerous tyme Whereunto is added a comfortable prayer to be vsed in this tyme. By Iohn Carpenter.</title>
            <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840623</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18020)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1061:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Time complaining, giueth a most godly admonition, and very profitable instruction to England in this our dangerous tyme Whereunto is added a comfortable prayer to be vsed in this tyme. By Iohn Carpenter.</title>
                  <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1588]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication dated 30 June 1588.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TIME</hi> Complaining, giueth a moſt godly <hi>admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and very profitable Inſtruction</hi> to England in this our dangerous Tyme.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added a comfortable prayer to be vſed in this Tyme. By <hi>IOHN CARPENTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. 1.</bibl> Euerie thing hath a Tyme, yea all that is vnder the Heauen, hath his conuenient ſeaſon.</q>
            <figure>
               <q>NON SOLO PANE VIVET HOMO: <bibl>Luke 4</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Verbum Dei manet in aeternum:</q>
               <p>I W</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John WIndet</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Worſhipfull mine</hi> especiall good friends, John VVal<hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rond of Bouy Eſquire, &amp; to Miſtris</hi> Iane W. his wife the bleſſing of <hi>of God be multiplied and continued.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great deſire and godlie delight, which J knowe to be in you both, to heare, reade and meditate in the Law of GOD, with that bleſſed man, whom Dauid deſcribeth: the bringing vp of your children with Abraham in the way of the Lord, and the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of your family in godlines, with your worthie examples vnto others, and vertues thereunto correspondent (beſides your manifolde friendſhippes towards me, your poore neighbour):
<pb facs="tcp:5147:3"/> haue often times moued me to praiſe GOD for you, and to commend your happie lot: And at this time to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſome parte of my gratefull good will, by ſending vnto you this little token (the complaint of Tyme). I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to accept it gladly at my handes, in regarde of my good will, chiefly in respect of the thing itſelfe, which (though as briefe a Jonas Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Niniue) expreſſeth greate matter for inſtruction, admonition, exhortation, commination, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, in all pietie. The Lord make vs thankefull for his gratious benefites, and ſo to vſe the happie Time of our peace, that our great prosperitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond other Nations, may rather fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vs, than hinder vs in that good
<pb facs="tcp:5147:3"/> courſe of godlines which we haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne, to the attaining of eternall life in Chriſt Ieſu. And that howſoeuer all the world be affected, we may fully reſolue to ſerue the Lorde as Joſua did, with our families: and not forget to pray vnto GOD with Heſter and her Maidens. Then ſhall wee enioy the benefite of our bleſſed time with Hezekias, and obtaine that ſafete ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our enemies, which other godlie haue obtayned by the mercie and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindnes of our good GOD. To whoſe bleſſed protection I commend you and yours. London, this laſt of June, 1582.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your W. Poore Neighbout and friend in Chriſt Ieſu</hi> Iohn Carpenter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:4"/>
            <head>To all true Engliſh heartes: <hi>faith, peace, thankefulnes, and</hi> all godlineſſe is wiſhed <hi>in the Lord our</hi> Sauiour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE greater your bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites are, which ye haue receiued from the Lord (deere brethren) the more ſhoulde bee your thankfulnes vnto him: and hauing much forgeuen you, ye ſhould with Mary alſo loue much, ye haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed a moſt bleſſed &amp; long time of peace and proſperitie, vnder our moſt gratious, godlie and ſoueraigne Lady Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, whom GOD long preſerue: and through her Chriſtian gouerment, ſuch excellent bleſſings, both for the bodie and the Soule, as the like no nation vnder Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at this day doeth enioy, for which the Lord expecteth your thankful heartes and faithfull loue towards him. But alas, your long peace &amp; proſperitie hath brought too
<pb facs="tcp:5147:4"/> many men into ſuch a careleſſe ſecurity &amp; contempt of the true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo long vſed amongſt you, that thereby the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of ſo bleſſed a time is iuſtlie occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to lament, and to wiſhe rather an ende of her courſe, than that her continuance ſhould yeeld long Libertie to ſuch men, ſo to abuſe the Lord &amp; his creatures, by their horrible ſinnes and iniquities. As the old Iſraelites recompenced their long peace with al kinde of vngodlines: ſo haue Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe men rewarded the Lorde euill for good, to the great griefe of his Soule, the ſorow of the true Engliſhe heartes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of his bleſſings. The benefit of their time alſo they either doe not knowe, or haue forgotten it: for they endeuour not to vſe her, but euery way to abuſe her, and waſt out the time in their worldlie vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which being once let gon, is neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called againe. Neyther may you thinke, that only the Lorde is greued, your ſelues are ſory, and Time lamenteth: but that alſo all the Creatures of GOD (as Paule teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) <note place="margin">Ro. 8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:5"/> which ſenie for mans vſe, feeling how monſtruouſly they are abuſed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhoulde in godlines vſe them with thankfulnes, doe altogether in one harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; conſent grone &amp; ſigh for ſpeedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, not willing, as it were, to ſerue any longer to the benefite of ingratefull men. And that, were it not, for your ſakes which truſt in your Lorde (as in Ioſua his houſe vnder ſo gratious a princeſſe) which praie heartely to the Lorde euen in the night when others ſleep, which performe true fidelitie and obedience to GOD and your Soueraigne: it coulde not otherwiſe bee, but that the treacheries conſpired, and horrible plagues threatned againſt vs would take effect: which yet the vngodly conſider not, and therefore they endeuour neither repentance nor holines of life, nor vſe time, nor to take time therunto. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, I beſeech you, for the tender mercies of Chriſt, that you hold on, as ye haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne in faithfulnes and true obedience to GOD and your Queene, to liue in vnitie
<pb facs="tcp:5147:5"/> and loue within your ſelues, and to fight againſt your enemies with that Spirituall Armor which Saint Paule hath appointed you. Then ſhal ye be ſtronger than your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <note place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> be they neuer ſo manie, and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beate downe the verie hammer of the earth to his ſhame &amp; confuſion. Then ſhall Goliath fall downe before Dauid, &amp; Senacherib before Hezekias yea Siſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſhall periſh before Deborah, Haman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Heſter, and proud Holofernes ſhalbe ſlaine by a womans hand. The Lord giue vs his grace, to redeeme the time becauſe the dayes are euill, to know the time of our viſitation, and what belongeth to our peace, to ſeeke the Lord, whiles he may be found, and praie vnto him now whiles he is neare: that wee may thereby enioy the benefite of our happie time, that the true hearted may reioyce in ſpirite, that the Creatures may be willing to ſerue for our comfort; and that the Lorde may bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thereby the ſooner to lead vs to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting peace through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rather yours then mine owne in Chriſt. I. C</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:6"/>
            <head>Tyme complaineth, for that ſhe is ſo vainely conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of worldly men, as wearie of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen high <hi>Iehoue</hi> did men embrace</l>
               <l>In Paradize, with great good wil,</l>
               <l>Then Ladie <hi>Tyme</hi> had pleaſant face,</l>
               <l>And did with him reioyce her fill:</l>
               <l>But when man fell, and ſinned ſore,</l>
               <l>She wyſht to die, and liue no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O worthie power, that me began,</l>
               <l>And framed man a Saint of ioy</l>
               <l>But oh alas to ſinfull man,</l>
               <l>That did procure his owne annoy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Which cauſed <hi>Time</hi> to loath his lore,</l>
               <l>And wiſh to end, and be no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea, though the Lord hath proffered peace.</l>
               <l>In Chriſt his ſonne, for all his crime:</l>
               <l>Yet Lo alas, men ſtill encreaſe</l>
               <l>Their faithleſſe facts, and waſt out <hi>Time.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhould not <hi>Time,</hi> then wiſh therefore,</l>
               <l>To leaue her life, and liue no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:6"/>
               <l>Although it be mans proper crime,</l>
               <l>Which doth deſerue the chiefe diſpraiſe:</l>
               <l>Yet euerie man cries out of <hi>Time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſayth, <hi>how euill are theſe our dayes?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if Dame <hi>Time,</hi> and daies began,</l>
               <l>This noyſome harme to euerie man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What eares can heare to be belyed?</l>
               <l>What tongue would taſt the bytter gall?</l>
               <l>What noſe would poyſoned ayres abide?</l>
               <l>What ſight would ſee his loftie fall?</l>
               <l>What ſence can ſerue to daylie payne?</l>
               <l>And how ſhould <hi>Time</hi> mens ſinnes ſuſtaine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Heuah</hi> cracks Gods right decree:</l>
               <l>By <hi>Satans</hi> ſhiftes, and <hi>Adam</hi> falles.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Cayn</hi> killes <hi>Abell</hi> cruelly.</l>
               <l>The ſonnes of <hi>Seth</hi> to luſt be thralls,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cham</hi> can diſcloſe his fathers ſhame:</l>
               <l>And breaſtes do burne in <hi>Sodoms</hi> flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The daughters both of aged <hi>Lot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can frame a frawde for ſoire <hi>Sire:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Abſolon,</hi> now feareth not,</l>
               <l>His fathers heart to ſet on fire.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Eſau</hi> voweth <hi>Iacobs</hi> bloud,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ioſephs</hi> breathren thinck no good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:7"/>
               <l>Such are the ſinnes that ſwell and ſway,</l>
               <l>In wofull wretched worldlie place:</l>
               <l>Theſe be the dolours of this day,</l>
               <l>That frame by fraud <hi>Time</hi> to deface:</l>
               <l>And theſe be they (alas) which ſtand</l>
               <l>Now entertayn'd in euery Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah wretched wightes, may <hi>Time</hi> therefore,</l>
               <l>With griefe complaine, with ſorrows crie:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould I liue, and any more,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe vnto ſuch bondage tye?</l>
               <l>Should worldlie men thus God requite</l>
               <l>Ingratefullie with ſuch deſpite?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Should <hi>England</hi> now gin to recoile,</l>
               <l>And yeld to that which God doth hate?</l>
               <l>Then <hi>England</hi> ſhall full ſhortlie toyle,</l>
               <l>and groane her griefes and ſtaggring ſtate:</l>
               <l>Except Repentance timelie turne</l>
               <l>From her the wrath, which now doeth burne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For loe, the inſtrumentes of Ire</l>
               <l>Are readie preſt, and draw them nye:</l>
               <l>The Lion, Woulfe and dragon dire,</l>
               <l>The Foxes with the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> flie,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Satyres,</hi> fawnes, and ſpirites of hell,</l>
               <l>Do ſtand and daunce where men do dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:7"/>
               <l>Therefore (O Land) thy languiſh flye,</l>
               <l>Be wiſe in <hi>Time,</hi> looke well about,</l>
               <l>Repent with auncient <hi>Niniuie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yer God do blotte thine honour out:</l>
               <l>Els Ladie <hi>Time</hi> yet will implore,</l>
               <l>That ſhe might ſleepe, and wake nomore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhall thy friends lament thy lorne,</l>
               <l>Then will thy foes clap hands and ioy:</l>
               <l>Then may mens mindes be rent and torne,</l>
               <l>And pleaſant places lodge annoy:</l>
               <l>Then Ladie <hi>Time</hi> no more will turne,</l>
               <l>To build the walles that foes ſhall burne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Gratious God that lodgeſt loue</l>
               <l>In breaſt diuine with mercies hie,</l>
               <l>With pitie yet this people proue,</l>
               <l>And ſaue our ſoules from miſerie.</l>
               <l>Grant Grace and <hi>Time,</hi> as erſt of yore</l>
               <l>That we may praiſe thee euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="envoy">
               <lg>
                  <l>Though mirth &amp; paſtime haue their tydes,</l>
                  <l>when peace and ſafety Sway:</l>
                  <l>Yet now the Time exhorteth men,</l>
                  <l>to wepe, to faſt, to pray.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:8"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Here followeth a very profitable dialogue betweene <hi>Tyme</hi> and <hi>England:</hi> mouing all <hi>perſons within this land to eſteeme of Gods</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies thankefully, to repent, and tend to the end of <hi>their deliuerance, by ſeruing God in holineſſe &amp;</hi> righteouſneſſe before him, without delaie.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Time</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe leaue and let me reſt in peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh</hi> England, <hi>be content:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It doth me good, to thinke on reſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For why, my Joyes be ſpent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I loue not thus to languiſh long,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay rather let me die,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sith all the Creatures in their kinde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reſound this Harmonie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh come (O Chriſt) and ſet vs free,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From bondage, Payne, and Synne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And quickely ende the tedious toyles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That wee doe labour in.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah Lord! Sould I abide this thrall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This anguiſh, Griefe and woe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That for the ſinnes of ſinfull ſoules</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ſuffer? Surely, No.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor could I be content (except</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That thou haddeſt ſo decreede)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To proffer foorth my tender pappes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their thankleſſe wombes to féede.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:8"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>Oh land, now go therefore to God</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>before that I go hence:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſeeching him to ſtay the ſtrokes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>of rightefull recompence.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>England.</speaker>
               <l>Ah <hi>Time;</hi> and art thou diſcontent</l>
               <l>with me? And wilt thou fly?</l>
               <l>Nay, rather tarrie as of yore:</l>
               <l>oh liue and do not dye.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Noah</hi> yet prepares his <hi>Arke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>as glad with me to dwell,</l>
               <l>And Lot is here (though faint for feare,</l>
               <l>and preacheth paſſing well.</l>
               <l>I haue the <hi>Arke</hi> in cuſtodie:</l>
               <l>oh <hi>Time,</hi> feare not therefore.</l>
               <l>And God is good and gratious yet</l>
               <l>to me, as once of yore.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> liueth in the land,</l>
               <l>yet <hi>Solomon</hi> doeth raigne:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Hezekias</hi> is in place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſiah</hi> doth remaine.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>the Apoſtles preach and pray,</l>
               <l>I haue the peace, and grace of God:</l>
               <l>oh <hi>Time,</hi> now therefore ſtay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:9"/>
               <speaker>Time.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe godlie Saints, theſe graces great,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>this peace, thou haſt miſuſed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnthankfully: and Lady</hi> Time</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>full often haſt abuſed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therefore the righteous do departe;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 1. pſal. 12. 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and periſh from the land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And faith and trueth from ſinfull Soules,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>will vaniſh out of hand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which if it come, calamities</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>will ſhortlie fall on thee:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thou no longer ſhalt diſdaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>theſe godlie Saintes, and me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For when that</hi> Noah <hi>is embarke,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 1. 10. Gen. 19. 22. 23. 24. 1. Sam. 4. 21. 22. 1. King. 2. and 11. and. 12. 2. King. 20. 17. 19. and 22. 19. 20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>the flouds will flaſh from ſkie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And when from</hi> Sodom Lot <hi>departs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>with fire will</hi> Sodom <hi>frie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If once the</hi> Arke <hi>be tane from thee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>thy glory wil departe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If</hi> Dauid <hi>die, and</hi> Solomon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>then woe ſhalbe thine heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If</hi> Hezekias <hi>thou entumb,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and <hi>Ioſias</hi> enterre:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas, who will praie for thy peace?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>who can thy plagues deferre?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if thy Sauiour thee forſake</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23. 37.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and holie Saintes, for ſinne:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:9"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>Alas, how can thy peace be kept:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and Candle holden in?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 3. 1. 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And as for me: If once I fly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am not ſtayd with hands:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As balde occaſion, that is turn'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and byrds ſcapt out of bands:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therefore, ſith</hi> Chriſt <hi>knocks at thy gate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>in</hi> Time <hi>him entertayne:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 3. 20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And pray him heartilie that</hi> Time</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>may longer yet remaine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then as one bound, I will abide,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 8. 20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>in hope, and him obey.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But ah, againſt his holie will,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>entreate me not to ſtaye.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>England.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 3.</note>Therefore to thee (O <hi>Chriſt</hi>) I come,</l>
               <l>my Refuge ſure and ſtrong:</l>
               <l>And I confeſſe with weeping eyes,</l>
               <l>that I haue doone thee wrong.</l>
               <l>For though with manie a benefite</l>
               <l>thou haſt enriched me:</l>
               <l>Yet moſt vnthanckfully I tooke</l>
               <l>the ſame (as all men ſee)</l>
               <l>I am the grateleſſe vine which nought <note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>but ſharp <hi>Labruſcas</hi> yeld:</l>
               <l>I am the fruitles figge tree ſet <note place="margin">Luk 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>within the fruitefull field.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:10"/>
               <l> I am the ſonne, that promiſed</l>
               <l>to worke, but went aſtray: <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 30. Luk. 17. 17. 18.</note>
               </l>
               <l>I am one of thoſe lepers nine,</l>
               <l>which thanckleſſe went away.</l>
               <l>I am not worthie of thy word:</l>
               <l>not worthie to be graced:</l>
               <l>Nor worthie of this peace, and prince,</l>
               <l>which thou in loue haſt placed.</l>
               <l>Therefore thy wiſdome worthily</l>
               <l>hath threatned to mee payn: <note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To take away my Soueraigne Queene,</l>
               <l>and grace from me againe.</l>
               <l>And well I know: If thus I ſhould</l>
               <l>conſume out pretious <hi>Time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By liuing in my lewd delight,</l>
               <l>encreaſing ſinfull crime:</l>
               <l>That plagues will ſoone light on my head,</l>
               <l>and vengeance ſhall enſue, <note place="margin">Deut 28.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To caſt a downe my hawtie hornes,</l>
               <l>and bring my fearefull rue.</l>
               <l>That all my fayre profeſſion, then</l>
               <l>ſhall nothing helpe at all,</l>
               <l>Nor beautie, policie nor ſtrength</l>
               <l>ſhall ſaue me from a fall.</l>
               <l>Then they that would not learne by lawes</l>
               <l>by wiſdom, threats and ſcholes:</l>
               <l>Shall learne at length by painfull proofe</l>
               <l>the rodde of froward fooles.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5147:10"/>
               <l> And finallie, then ſhall I crie,</l>
               <l>as forced thereupon,</l>
               <l>With tired <hi>Time,</hi> to vtter forth</l>
               <l>my <hi>Cairopenthicon.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">That is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of peereles time.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But ſeeing thy mercy (O good God) Dan. 9. 9</l>
               <l>in goodnes thou haſt ment</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſinner that returnes</l>
               <l>in time, and doth repent:</l>
               <l>Lette me reteine a faithfull hope</l>
               <l>of mercie, I thee praie:</l>
               <l>And graunt thy grace, and healthfull <hi>Time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>in peace, with me to ſtay.</l>
               <l>Oh let thy Candle giue me light:</l>
               <l>and baniſh night away.</l>
               <l>Oh let my Princeſſe raigne in peace,</l>
               <l>and let her foes decay.</l>
               <l>Oh giue her ioye, and comfort me,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Time</hi> no more may ſing,</l>
               <l>Her heauie <hi>Chronopenthicon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>but praiſe thee heauenly King.</l>
            </sp>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:11"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> That Praier is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in this our</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen that proud <hi>Senacherib</hi> had ſent to blaſpheme the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> to the greate diſcomfort and horror of godly king <hi>Hezekias</hi> and his people: <hi>Hezekias,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ordinary meane of defence by the calling of his ſtrong men together, and fortifieng the walles of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> knowing that the ſtrength of the Lord is farre aboue the might of man, and hee guideth euerie battell, as pleaſeth himſelf, repaireth vnto the Lord, humbleth himſelfe, proclaimeth a faſt, and praieth before the Lord with a faithfull heart, and hereby hee found the ſhining beames of Gods mercie on himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:5147:11"/> and his people. By this example, let vs bee moued in this time of extremitie, when all our enemies conſpire together againſt vs, to runne vnto our good God and craue the ayde of his hand to help and defend vs. For as he was to <hi>Hezekias,</hi> ſo to the godly now: as hee might ſay then, ſo wee ſay now: the Lord is our God, our rock, our defender in whom wee truſt, by whome we eſcape death: And turning vnto him with faithfull hearts and repentance let vs pray vnto him in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:12"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Godlie and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Praier.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt gratious God and merciful Sauior, we pray and beſeech thee to bee mercifull to our ſinnes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy greate mercie, as thou haſt forgeuen vs euen from our bondage in Egipt vntill now. Geue vs not ouer, O Lord, our moſt gratious father, leaſte the heathen which deſpiſe thee, behold our miſerie, and ſay in deriſion: loe where is now their God in whome they truſt? And although when a man putteth away his wife, and ſhe goeth from him and marieth with another, then the queſtion is: ſhould he reſort to her any more after that? And
<pb facs="tcp:5147:12"/> the land is vnpure and defiled, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fornication with many louers: yet <note place="margin">Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> turne vs againe (O GOD) and we ſhalbe turned. And becauſe thou art mercifull and of long ſuffring, louing and gentle to them that offende, not willing the death of a ſinner, but rather that hee ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte and liue, repreſſe the vehement heate of thy fire with godly pitie, ſtay thine hand from our deſtruction, and looke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably vnto our Soueraigne Princeſſe, Elizabeth thy ſeruant, as thou diddeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dauid, Hezekias and Ioſia, and ſo to the whole land. And ſend vs peace, yea an happie peace. Bleſſe vs al with thy ſpirite, defend vs with thy right hand, ſhrowd vs vnder thy wings againſt our enemies, that ſo we may ſerue thee in holines and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes al the daies of our liues. Let it not be ſayed: how long ſhall the land mourne, and all the herbs of the fielde periſh for the wickednes of them that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: let not the creatures haue ſuch cauſe for vs to deſire to leaue vs: let not Time ſay of
<pb facs="tcp:5147:13"/> vs: theſe be they that greue me, waſte mee out riotouſlie, make me complaine and wiſh to reſt and riſe no more. But let it bee ſaied: beholde the Lorde liueth for euer worthie of praiſe, becauſe hee hath bin mercifull vnto ſinners, cauſing them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, repent, and turne vnto him and be ſaued. And though thou once ſpakeſt to <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 1.</note> Ieremie againſt thy owne people being diſobedient vnto thee, ſaying: Though Moſes and Samuel ſtoode before mee, yet haue I no heart vnto this people, driue them away, that they may goe out of my ſight, ſome vnto death, ſome to the ſword, ſome to hunger and ſome to captiuitie: yet we knowe (O our good Lord) that when Ephraim was heard lamenting &amp; praying <note place="margin">Ier. 31. 18. of 6. 1. Io. 2. 10.</note> heartilie vnto them in his diſtreſſe thou thoughteſt vpon mercy, as a father pitying his owne children. And though Ionas cried out, deſtruction deſtruction againſt Niniuie: yet ſeeing them to turne from their euill waies, thou didſt repent, &amp; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not that euill vppon them. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:5147:13"/> preſume on GOD, to call for mercie vppon repentaunce, and let vs heare that ſounding in our eares, which Hezekias proclaymed in all his prouinces ſaieng: be not you ſtiffnecked like as were your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but yeld your ſelues vnto the Lord, <note place="margin">2. Chro. 30 8.</note> and enter into his holy place which hee hath ſanctified for euer: &amp; ſerue the Lord your God, &amp; the fearceneſſe of his wrath ſhalbe turned away from you. Let vs not only heare this, but obey this, that we may find the comfortable commoditie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Graunt vs grace (O father) to forſake our euill waies, &amp; our own imaginations, <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.</note> and turne hartilie vnto thee. Oh graunt, it that wee may put diſpleaſure betimes <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1 and. 12.</note> out of our hearts, and in ſeaſon remoue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from our bodies, that we may not any longer delight in Childhood and youth, which are vanities: that we may fruitfully remember thee in theſe our tender yeres, while we haue libertie to goe where wee liſt, before the Time of trouble come, and the dayes approach wherein wee ſhall crie
<pb facs="tcp:5147:14"/> out: oh theſe daies be euill: they doe not delight vs. Graunt (O good Lord) that thy grace may guide vs, that we may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, but moſt gratefullie entertaine our faithfull Iacob: if for nothing els, yet in regard of theſe our preſent commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereof his departure wil ſhortlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue vs, if we continue vnthankfull. That wee may reteine him as good Abraham and Lot did the Angels, as Rahab did the Spies of Ioſuah, as the widows did the prophets, Elias &amp; Elizeus as Zacheus and Martha did our ſauiour Chriſt, and as Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia did the Apoſtles: that ſo wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy mercy, enioy thy fauour, abound with bleſſings, bee encreaſed in our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, defended in thy faith: and preſerued from our enemies, whome, wee beſeeche thee, either to conuert and bring home to thee, or elſe to caſt downe before vs: that wee being in peace vnder our vines, and <note place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 25. 2. 2. King. 17.</note> figge trees may freelie ſerue thee to thy glorie. Graunt wee pray thee (O good Lord) that though the ramping Lyons of
<pb facs="tcp:5147:14"/> Samaria ſeeke to ſpoile vs, wee may not haue any iuſt cauſe to feare, becauſe by faith in thee we ſhall ſodainly reſiſt them: thy feare (O father) ſhall ſhield vs and their treacheries and deueliſh pretences ſhall fall on their owne heads. Though the flies <note place="margin">Iſa. 7. 8.</note> that ſwarme about the water of Egipt, and the Bees that be in the Aſſyrians land flie together, and light in al the deſolate val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes, in the hoales of the ſtones, and vpon all thorny and buſhye places: yet we may not then feare, nor bee diſcouraged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue conſpired wickedlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs thy people: againſt our gratious Soueraigne Ladie, thine anoynted, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee our GOD, whom we ſerue, whom we honour, on whom we depend for whoſe cauſe we bee perſecuted, vnder whoſe banner wee fight, and through whom we ſtand: which in mercie to vs, &amp; in iuſtice to them, haſte promiſed vppon our repentance, and hope in thee, and thou wilt ſurelie performe (if our ſinnes hinder it not, and prouoke thee to wrath againſt
<pb facs="tcp:5147:15"/> vs) that it ſhall not ſo goe forth &amp; come to paſſe, as they haue imagined. And ſo long as thou art pleaſed with vs, wee ſhall not bee deliuered into the hand of bragging Holofernes. Though the great red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon <note place="margin">Iud 2. 5. Reu. 12 and 20. 2.</note> with ſeauen heads and tenne hornes bend his force againſt vs, though with his taile he draw downe the third part of the ſtarres of heauen, though he perſecute the woman and her child; though the kings of <note place="margin">Pſal 2. 2 and. 99.</note> the Earth and the mightie Potentats of the world riſe vp and take counſell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt thee, and thine annoynted: though the people tremble, the Earth bee moued, the heauens bend, the Sea do rage, and all the Creatures looke ſower, and cry for deliuerance: yet ſhal we not be diſmaid we ſhal not tremble, nor be ſhaken, as long as we truſt in thee, leane vnto thee, and reſt vpon thee and the Rock of thy trueth: for thou art our God for euer, mighty, ſtrong, terrible and glorious, which ſitteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubins: thou art greate in the middeſt of Sion, &amp; high aboue all the
<pb facs="tcp:5147:15"/> Nations of the earth: thou heareſt them, thou ruleſt them, thou ſendeſt them forth and reſtrayneſt the furie of Leuiathan in <note place="margin">Iob 40. 1 and 41. 1</note> the Sea, and of Behemoth in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Be thou with vs continually, hold vs by thy right hand ſtrongly; guide vs by thy counſell wiſelie, and receiue vs into glorie victoriouſlie. And if thou be with vs, who dare bee againſt vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For thou arte ſtronger then al they that be in the world. Therefore with a true faith, and heartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance we come vnto thee. Bleſſe vs (O father) both without and within. Be thou our gard: thy word our guide, thy ſpirite our comfort, thy Sonne our Sauiour, and thy ſeruant our Soueraigne Lady Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth our louing Mother in Iſrael. Giue vs grace (O heauenlie King) to accompte the Time of grace pretiouſe, to redeeme the Time, becauſe the dayes are euil: to vſe the Creatures gratefully, to entertayne faithe hope and charitie, and grant, that we may no longer by meanes of our tranſgreſſions conſtraine Iacob to departe, Ieremie t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:5147:16"/> Ioſeph to be aflicted, the Creatures to grone, &amp; the peereles Time to ſighe and crie for perpetuall reſt. But rather that we our ſelues may bewaile our ſinnes &amp; the miſeries of this life, with the godly, with the Creatures, with Time, and to crie out vnto thee Lord in heartie and humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: O come good Lorde, come Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <note place="margin">Reu. 22. 20.</note> how long ſhall the vngodlie triumph? The iuſt be afflicted? the creatures groane for deliuerance? Finiſh ſoone theſe ſinfull dayes: caſt downe the Dragon, the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, Antichriſt and all thine enemies into the bottomles pit of euerlaſting torment, &amp; receiue thine holy elected Saintes into thy ſweet boſome, with this comfortable call: come yee bleſſed, receiue the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 34.</note> prepared for you from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. Into the which King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome we beſeech thee, O louing father to receiue vs, for the ſake of thy deare ſonne Ieſus, to whom with thee and the holie ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, bee all honour, glorie power and dominion, now &amp; for euermore Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5147:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
